Bertha Johnson Collection,
Bertha Johnson Collection
1848-1956
Johnson, Bertha F., 1880-
1.2 linear feet
Mss.arc
New York Academy of Medicine Library. Rare Book Room.
Historical Note
Little is known about the life and work of Bertha Florence Johnson. According to the American Medical Directory for 1931, Johnson was born in 1880 and received her degree from the New York Medical Hospital and College for Women in 1905. She was licensed in 1925, but was not practicing in 1931. She was listed as located in Granville Summit, Pennsylvania. Bertha Johnson's sister, Pearl Johnson, was the partner of Benjamin Tucker, an American anarchist.
Scope and Content
The collection is largely comprised of ephemeral materials on medical subjects from the office of Dr. Bertha F. Johnson. Ephemera on agricultural and culinary topics are also present, as well as a few personal papers of Dr. Johnson and Emery Andrews.
Arrangement of Collection
While the collection has not been arranged into series, three rough categories can be found - personal papers, medical ephemera, and culinary and agricultural ephemera. Within the medical ephemera, items have been organized alphabetically by publisher when the publisher is represented by two or more items.
Index Terms
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the catalog of The New York Academy of Medicine Library. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Ephemera.; Andrews, Emery.
Container List
  - Bertha Johnson Personal Papers, undated, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Emery Andrews Personal Papers, undated, 1900-1931 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Medical Ephemera - Appeal Publishing Co., 2 items (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Medical Ephemera - Battle Creek Sanitarium, 7 items (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Medical Ephemera - Bilhuber-Knoll Corp., 3 items (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Medical Ephemera - Cabinet Mfg. Co., 11 items (10 duplicates) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Medical Ephemera - S. H. Camp and Company, 3 items (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Medical Ephemera - Ciba Pharmaceutical Products, Inc., 13 items (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Medical Ephemera - Cole Chemical Co., 2 items (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Medical Ephemera - Dios Chemical Company, 5 items (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Medical Ephemera - Fowler and Wells, 3 items (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Medical Ephemera - Harrower Laboratory, Inc., 3 items (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Medical Ephemera - Life Extension Institute, 7 items (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Medical Ephemera - Lindlahr Sanitarium, 3 items (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Medical Ephemera - Merck and Co., 3 items (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Medical Ephemera - Metropolitan Life Insurance Company, 3 items (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Medical Ephemera - New Jersey. State Dept. of Health, 3 items (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Medical Ephemera - Pennsylvania. Dept. of Health, 23 items (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Medical Ephemera - Pennsylvania. Dept. of Health (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Medical Ephemera - Petrogalar Laboratories, 4 items (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Medical Ephemera - Physical Culture Publishing Co., 2 items (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Medical Ephemera - Purdue Frederick Company, 2 items (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Medical Ephemera - Taylor Instrument Companies, 6 items (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Medical Ephemera - Thos. Leeming and Co., Inc., 4 items (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Medical Ephemera - United States, 3 items (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Medical Ephemera - Winthrop Chemical Company (New York, N.Y.), 5 items (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Medical Ephemera - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Medical Ephemera - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Medical Ephemera - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Medical Ephemera - Miscellaneous, 1883-1909 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Medical Ephemera - Miscellaneous, 1919-1936 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Medical Ephemera - Miscellaneous, 1937-1943 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Culinary and Agricultural Ephemera - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Culinary and Agricultural Ephemera - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 34)
Provenance
The collection was donated by the New York Public Library, Division of Manuscripts and Archives, in 1988. It was removed from the Benjamin Tucker Papers.
These materials originally resided in the Benjamin Tucker Papers, held by the New York Public Library. The Bertha Johnson books, ephemera, and papers were separated from the Benjamin Tucker Papers and donated to the New York Academy of Medicine Library in 1988. The books donated have been cataloged individually and are part of our rare book collection.
The Sophia Smith Collection at Smith College holds Bertha F. Johnson's papers, and the Labadie Collection of the University of Michigan has correspondence between Johnson and Agnes Inglis.